If you're into AI filmmaking, then you
need to understand camera movements.
Static shot, zoom in, dolly out,
tracking shot, just to name a few.
>> It's called casual Friday.
>> I will show you 30 different shots and
explain to you how to prompt them, when
to use these, and what kind of intention
each and every movement has. I will also
leave a link in the description down
below with all of the assets with the
prompts, including a prompt generator
that you can use. So, you don't have to
pause this video, but you can just click
the website, copy the prompt from there,
and even customize the prompt to your
own liking to get the exact shot that
you want. To generate all of these
examples, I've used Hex Field, and the
main models I used within that is Sea
Dance and Kling. If you want to try this
out yourself, I would highly recommend
clicking the link in the description
down below, so you can get started.
We're going to start off with the
basics. These are the simple type of
shots that we all know, like static
shots, pan shots, whip shots. You just
might not know how to prompt them. If
you were to think of the camera with
these type of shots, then it's usually
positioned on a tripod. And these are
also the type of shots that you will be
the first to learn if you are learning
about filmmaking. So, shot number one is
a static shot. And you can play around
with close-ups, medium, wide, or extreme
close-ups. With a static shot, the
camera stays completely still. The
camera gears are locked, and they don't
move a millimeter. It forces the
audience to focus on the subject without
distraction. Even with those
limitations, you're still able to create
different type of shots, like close-ups,
medium shots, and even wide shots.
>> How long do I have to sit here?
>> Next up, we got pan or whip pan. When
you pan, the tripod stays still, but
your camera on top of it moves from the
left to the right, almost like someone
is shaking their head no. This action
allows you to scan the room, follow the
action of a character that was or show
something that was previously off
screen.
Then we got tilt up or tilt down. Tilt
up is similar to a pan, but instead of
shaking your head no, you're yawning.
You're nodding your head to say yes. You
tilt up and down to show, for example, a
tall building or showing someone's feet.
It could be a character looking up to a
giant that makes them look small and
weak or defeated. Then we got zooms, and
this is an interesting one because you
got not only like zoom ins, zoom outs,
but you also can play around with the
way of how you zoom in or out. For
example, you can do a slow zoom in to
set the mood. You can do a fast zoom in,
a crash zoom in. You can name it. There
is a zoom for it. But, the way you use
the zoom in AI filmmaking really matters
a lot when it comes to trying to portray
the mood that you're trying to bring
with that video. We're going to start
with a slow zoom in or slow zoom out.
When it comes to the slow zoom, it can
build tension depending on how slow it
is. It can make us focus on what the
character is saying since we are slowly
creeping towards them. I was there, but
I did not stop it.
The same also goes for the zoom out. It
can make us disassociate them from the
character or the subject that we're
looking at. It can also show more of the
environment, which makes our character
less significant. If you're thinking
about slow zoom ins, then obviously you
also have to think about fast zooms. A
fast zoom quickly changes the lens to
bring the subject closer or push them
away. It is quicker and more noticeable
than a slow zoom, but not quite as
aggressive as a crash zoom. Now, here's
an example when you can use a zoom in.
For example, in this scene where a
character makes a sudden discovery or
notices that something is wrong. Or when
a character suddenly becomes vulnerable
and gets a reality check or something
unexpected happens suddenly. Next up, we
have crash zooms. These are one of my
favorites. This is a camera technique
that is usually used in more of a
comedic way, but still does and has a
purpose in films that are a bit more
serious, like Kill Bill, for example.
You would use a crash zoom in in moments
where a sudden overwhelming shock or a
sudden realization or a comedic moment
is happening, but also to increase the
intensity and extra emphasis of what
someone is saying.
>> All of it.
>> Now, the crash zoom out is used to show
a character or an object in a very
absurd or chaotic wider environment.
Maybe also as a comedic moment. For
example, you have a guy in a suit, then
punch out and see that he's not even
wearing pants.
>> I don't see the problem.
It's called casual Friday.
>> Moving on, we need to talk about the
dolly shots, and particularly dolly in
and out. At first, you might think that
this is the same as a zoom in or a zoom
out, but it is actually different. With
a zoom in, the camera is standing in the
same place and the lens is zooming in.
With a dolly in or a dolly out, the
camera is moving while the lens stay the
same. This kind of dolly shots can
create a realistic feeling where it
feels like you're actually moving closer
or leaving a character behind. So, for
example, when you're creeping in a
hallway towards a figure that you do not
know how to react to, it could lead to a
jump scare. Or, you would use a dolly
out when a character is defeated,
isolated, or lonely. It's similar to the
zoom out, but this is maybe more
intimate because it feels like you're
actually leaving the character behind,
too. Next up, we got physical moves, and
this is the part that Hollywood loves
the most. These are the moves that
require big crews, large budget, and
good camera equipment because these are
shots where the camera is traveling
physically from side to side, straight
up and down, or just sliding smoothly
around an object or a person. You should
imagine the camera moving on a track
alongside with your character, walking
around it, circling around it, or giving
it you that three-dimensional feeling to
it. The first physical movement that I
like is a truck shot. This is where the
camera is moving physically sideways in
a straight line while pointing in the
same direction. Because it moves
parallel to the environment. You can use
this to travel alongside a moving
character that is walking. The camera
will track it smoothly, and it will
follow that character. Then we got
pedestal up or pedestal down. Now, this
is basically where the camera is moving
straight up and straight out without
tilting its head. This could be used to
show a character from his feet, then all
the way to his head, and that could be
used as a way to introduce that
character. Then we got the slider shot.
The slider shot is a short controlled
slide from left to right or right to
left using a short reel that can be used
to create a sliding effect in a tight
space. For example, when a detective is
leaning over a messy desk. While the
slider slowly moves across the table
with the evidence visible. Next up, we
got push past or pass by shot. You use
this when you want to enter a room or
catch a character doing something that
is hidden. For example, a mechanic works
in a garage and the camera is pushing
forward past the cables. The obstacle is
behind the lens as he pauses over the
tools. Next up, we got arc shot. If you
think about the arc shot, you also might
think about orbiting shots, and these
are quite similar. An orbit shot where
it turns fully 360 around the subject.
With the arc shot, you stand at the back
of your character and then you slowly
shift around your character to see their
face, for example. The orbit shot is a
bit more crazy. You show this to show a
crazy action scene or to show a wildly
fantasy world, for example. Then we got
subject camera movements. These are
different variations of tracking shots.
Now, movies are all about following
characters on a journey. A tracking shot
physically moves the camera to keep up
with them. You can follow behind the
character to build suspense, walk
backward in front of them to see their
facial expressions, or even aggressively
chase them during a fast action scene.
By moving at the exact same speed as
your subject, the audience feels like
they are right in the action. The
tracking shot. A tracking shot is a shot
that physically moves the camera through
the scene. For example, when a chef is
walking through a very crowded busy
restaurant kitchen, while the camera
glides along with him, keeping him
centered as he walks along the line of
cooks who are cooking with hot pans on
the side of the screen. Then you have
the follow shots. This can also be the
follow shot over the shoulder. This is
when the camera is tracking behind the
character's back after using an
over-the-shoulder view. This forces the
audience to see the world exactly how
our character sees it. This is used to
build suspense and curiosity. For
example, a teenager is slowly walking
down a dark, creaky basement staircase
and the camera follows closely behind
his shoulder, making the audience feel
like they're stepping down into the dark
along with him. Next up, we got reverse
tracking. Here, the camera's moving
backwards. It takes the same pace as the
character that walks forward and the
camera is locked to the facial
expression or forced to pay attention to
their emotion. It could be a shot of a
singular person or two people having a
conversation. Then we got side tracking.
This is when a subject is running or
walking. Here, the camera is basically
parallel to the subject traveling
sideways. This can be used in a
situation where the character is
running, for example, an athlete on
track running as fast as he can. Then we
got low tracking shots. Here, the camera
is basically pointed to below the belt
and is usually not focused on the eyes.
For example, a cowboy is mysterious and
walks until he's not alone. And we
follow his steps while we are tracking
his boots. Next up, vehicle tracking.
Vehicle tracking is basically where we
track a vehicle at high speed, a moving
car, a motorcycle, a train and this can
be used during the travel scene, usually
an action scene. Then chase shots. This
is aggressive and messy, a graphic
scramble to keep up with the
unpredictable action as if the camera is
running behind trying to follow up the
action as best as he can. Like when our
hero is trying to escape from a
terrifying beast like a bear or a
bigfoot or whatever it is and the camera
is trying his best to follow up with the
action. Then we got human camera
movements and these are some of my
favorite because this, especially with
AI, makes a video feel real. Like
handheld shots, slight shakiness. You
can feel that it is recorded by humans.
And that is the kind of thing that when
you have too polished of a zoom or like
a slider shot where it will feel robotic
or almost too smooth. With a human
camera movement, it's the perfect way to
show panic, dizziness, or a character
losing control, for example. One of the
most common is handheld shots. By
letting the camera shake lightly, just
like a person holding it, will make it
feel more raw and realistic. This can be
used to make a fictional scene feel more
real. Or when a family is gathering
around a kitchen table during a tense
argument, and the camera shakes lightly
and shifts between the faces, making the
viewer feel uncomfortable. You ride that
with them in the room. Then we have body
mounted camera or snorricam. This is
basically snapping the camera directly
to the actor's chest, straight back at
their face. Because the camera is locked
to their torso, their head stays
completely frozen in the center of the
screen, while the entire background
shakes violently around them. You can
use this to illustrate hysteria or being
drunk or being in a massive panic
attack. For example, when a man is
panicking inside a crowded flashing
nightclub as he stumbles towards the
exit. Like Spider-Man also used a scene
like this. Let's move on and go over to
the big moves, aerial and crane shots.
With these type of shots, you usually
need expensive equipment like drones or
even cranes. With AI, like all of these
shots, it's a lot simpler to do. We're
going to start off with a crane up and a
crane down. It is when you move the
camera vertically through a space using
a massive mechanical arm. That is what a
crane is. The crane lifts up the
audience away from your subject and can
be used for the ending of a scene or a
film, leaving behind the character,
showing a place around them. For
example, when we have a traveler sitting
on a train station bench, the camera
lifts straight up into the air, rising
above the station roof, revealing a
massive city layout surrounding it. Then
we have the drone. We can do a flyover,
a push in, a pull back, orbit, whatever
you name it, you can do with the drone.
When it comes to drone moves, those can
be used for high altitude camera
movements. Those moves are usually
smooth unless you use FPV. They show of
landscapes, but they can also be used to
push towards an object. It can also go
through tight spaces like windows or
doors without the limitation of heavy
ground gear. When you think of drones,
you might also think of helicopter
shots. When it comes to helicopter
shots, they are like high altitude
shots, but a bit more gradual and a bit
more steady. They can be used for grand
opening scenes, immediately establishing
a massive set or environment, which you
can fly over or show of a car driving
away or even following a car. Let's end
it off with special shots. Especially
with AI, these shots are now easier than
ever. We're talking about a first-person
view, for example. This puts the lens
exactly where the character's eyes would
be. You can use this when you want the
viewer to feel like they're seeing the
world directly through that character's
eyes. Then we have tilt shift. This is a
neat visual effect that blurs the top
and the bottom of the frame. It is used
to make a real, full-size location feel
exactly like a tiny model world. Tilt
shift lenses are usually really
expensive, too. But, of course, with AI,
that doesn't apply to you. Infinite
zoom. Here, you would have to think of a
continuous zoom that is inwards and that
is never stopping. The camera's
constantly zooming in into the next
world. This is perfect to surreal
reveals or dream sequences. Then we have
earth zoom out. Now, this is one of
those things that you might have seen on
TikTok, but this shot is actually quite
cool. This is where the camera's rapidly
moving upward towards the sky. It is
used to move from a small human moment
or an object or a building all the way
out to the city or country or the world.
The last shot that is quite cool to use
with AI is the time lapse. A time lapse
usually will cost you a lot of time.
But, with AI, you can make these super
fast and easy. This is where the camera
stays still and it is recording the same
scene for a long amount of time. For
example, see weather changes or crowd
moving or light changes. When it takes
like these short frames, it creates this
super cool effect where you can see all
of the movement if you speed it up where
it has to record it the entire day. So
now you hopefully understand all the
different camera movements that can be
used in AI. If you want to try this out
yourself, I'll leave a link to Higgs
Field in the description down below.
Also, make sure that you use the cheat
sheet to help you generate these shots.
You can just simply copy them and then
you can use them yourself in any
generation that you're planning to do.
Make sure to click the video that's on
the screen right now if you want to
learn more about AI filmmaking.